本片關於未來的氣候的刻劃，是根據主流科學的預測所建構。
所有從以前到現在的鏡頭都是真實的新聞與紀錄片片段
轉譯、翻譯：謝綸謝綾字幕組
愚蠢的年代
北極
歡迎來到全球檔案館，
Welcome to the global archive,
一個座落於挪威北方800公里處的巨大建築。
a vast storage structure located 800km north of Norway.
來自世界各地博物館的文物。
It contains the artwork from every national museum.
動物標本層層堆疊。
There are pickled animals stack up two by two.
所有的電影、所有書籍、所有科學報告，
Every film, every book, every scientific report,
都被儲存在一排排的電腦裡。
all stored on banks of servers.
現在會有這樣的狀況，
But the conditions we are experiencing now,
其實是人類在西元2015以前所累積的惡果。
were actually cause by our behavior in the period leading up to 2015.
換句話說，我們曾經有機會拯救自己。
In other words, we could've saved ourselves
我們曾經有機會拯救自己。
We could've saved ourselves.
但我們沒做，不可思議!
But we didn't, it's amazing!
我們那個時候到底在想甚麼?
What state of mind were we in,
面對地球即將滅亡，卻一點也不在乎?
to face extinction, and simply shrug it off?
不管天生的或是不感興趣，(印度人)都比較內向。
By nature or by disinterest, there is always an introvert.
多年來，你知道的，航空業都需要一個門面
For years, you know, the non-business need, need a face…
不拉不拉不拉…，一種性格。
blah, blah, blah… personality.
2005年，32歲的企業家，Jeh Wadia
The year 32-year-old entrepreneur Jeh Wadia,
成立了印度第三家廉價航空公司。
he started up India's third low-cost airline, in 2005.
輪到印度起飛了，輪到印度開始發展商業了。
Time for India's now, the time for developing business in India is now.
他公司有1200個員工，大部份的人連飛機都沒上去過。
He's got 1200 employees, most of whom have never set foot on an airplane.
我們可能會遭遇到甚麼樣的劫機犯?
What are the different kinds of hijackers that you might have?
一點小煙怕甚麼? 一點小火就被嚇得逃跑啦?
Why are you scared of a little smoke? Do want to be scared and run of fire?
這不是一個玩具捏，不是一罐香水捏，你一定要瞄準，拿穩，就這樣。
It's not a toy, it's not a perfume bottle, you've got to aim it, hold it. That's it.
當 Stelios Haji-Ioannou 成立 Easy Jet 的時候，我去過倫敦，
I was at London at the time, where Stelios Haji-Ioannou,you know, uh, he created the EZ jet,
我被他們成功的方式所吸引。
and I was fascinated with basically how he did it.
疏散，疏散
Evacuate, evacuate…
往這裡跑，往這裡跑
Go this way, go this way…
我們提供的票價從600盧比一路到1盧比都有。
We've been offering fares from 600 rupees, ok, all the way down to 1 rupee.
有多少人付得起1盧比的費用，我想每個印度人應該都可以。
How many people can afford a 1 rupee fare? I would imagine every single Indian can.
黃包車伕可以，僕人也可以。
That the, a rickshaw driver can, and servants.
現在2005年了，在個一億人的國家中，
You know in year 2005, I mean, you know,
只有菁英階級的人可以搭飛機，很荒謬。
having a elite class who can fly in a country of a billion people, it's ridiculous.
搜尋：到2010年為止因為氣候改變造成的災害。
Search: visible impacts of climate change leading up to 2010.
華氏101度，有史以來最熱的一天。
101 degrees Fahrenheit, it's the hottest day ever recorded.
印度發生歷年最大的降雨，700人將面臨死亡的威脅。
700 people are now feared dead after the strongest ever-recorded days rain fall in India's history.
官方消息指出，去年為墨爾本史上乾旱最嚴重的一年。
Now, it's official, the past year has been the driest in Melbourne's history.
沙漠每年以3英哩的速度向外擴張。
The dessert is advancing at the phenomenal rate of 3 miles every year.
南極的冰川坍塌的速率，比所有人預期的快。
Dozens of Antarctic ice shelves collapsing faster than anyone predicted.
18個國家都被洪水淹沒，150萬民眾受害。
18 countries are under water, and one and a half million people are affected.
當我第一次看到這群山。
那種美。
實在很美好。
那真的就是一見鐘情。
我在1956年通過了山嶽嚮導訓練
Fernand Pareau攀爬了歐洲最高峰，白朗峰，超過150次。
Fernand Pareau has climbed Europe's highest mountain Mont Blanc over 150 times.
他現在要當一個英國家庭的嚮導。
Here he's guiding a family from England.
嗨囉。我是Piers，你好嗎?
Pierre?
Pierre.
我太太，Lisa。
很高興認識你。
現在就親了唷?
酷唷。
謝謝
所以你們想要去爬山?
對對對
有一點。
你們想在冰河上行走嗎?
不不不
只要看就好。
看就好。
但我們可以去上面行走。
好好
那很棒。
嗯嗯嗯
82歲，全法國最老的"上班族"。
At 82, Fernand is the oldest guy still working in France.
他的一生見證了山川的巨大改變。
All his lifetime he witnessed huge changes in the mountains.
當你年輕的時候
溫度...如何?
怎麼樣?
我年輕的時候氣候是甚麼樣子嗎?
我們曾經有很棒的夏天，但絕對沒有現在這麼熱。
以前我們曾在這裡放牧。
牠們會走在冰河的邊緣，
然後上去吃草。
是，是。
那裡吃草很不錯。
但現在都沒了。
以前這裡沒梯子，
我們只須走幾步路就可以到冰河。
你看，這裡從1945到現在，差不多融化了有150公尺這麼深。
地質學家可能可以給更精確的數字，但我看起來是這麼多。
這邊梯子下面有一段比較長的間隔唷。
Now, there's an elaborate extension on the bottom here.
今年他們又加裝了另一段梯子。
所以今年冰河又融化了差不多7到10公尺。
天氣較熱的時候甚至會融化更多。
不可思議。
想到現在是阿爾卑斯山的12月，很讓人覺得不可思議。
Extraordinary to think that these are the Alps in December.
山另一頭的夏慕尼市區(著名滑雪、冰川景點)，
Here in Chamonix is across the Alps,
溫度高的嚇人，雪少得可憐。
there's a dramatic lack of snow, and exceptionally warm temperatures.
我們似乎已經可以看到未來的樣子了。
It is a glimpse into the future.
未來50年內，歐洲超過一半的滑雪場將因全球暖化而關閉。
More than half of ski resort in Europe could shut down in the next 50 years because of global warming.
所以沒有人可以滑雪了，沒甚麼，重點是這不是甚麼壞事。
So nobody goes skiing, big deal. The thing is it's not bad, is it? That's the whole point.
沒雪可滑或是冰川融化，並不是真的重點。
The fact you can't get skiing anymore or the glaciers are melting is not really the point,
重點是這代表了地球越來越不穩定。
the point is that signals that basically the earth is destabilizing.
所有使得生命得以存活的規則都開始改變了
And all the norms that have allowed life to exist are changing.
現在因為全球暖化，很多事情都不一樣了。
我覺得現在只分成兩個季節
冬天過後毫無徵兆的直接變成夏天
我們該怎麼辦?
我不知道。
冰河每天都融化越來越多。
列出有關：氣候變遷、重大事件，時至今日。
List: climate change, major events, up to the present day.
這是卡崔妠颶風登陸的前幾天，
This is a couple of days before Katrina struck.
大部分的居民都遵守撤離市區的命令。
Most people are following the evacuation order in getting out of the city.
但在紐奧良土生土長的Alvin DuVernay沒有想要離開。
But New Orleans-borne Alvin DuVernay had no intention of moving.
我星期六早上起來聽到鄰居的吵鬧聲，
I got up at Saturday morning and there's a buzz in the neighborhood,
大家一團亂，我說：「是安怎?」
everybody were running around and I was like what's up, what's up?
原來是颶風要來了。
You know, the hurricane's coming.
我上網查了一下，所有資訊都顯示颶風對準我們直撲而來，正中紅心。
I checked on the web and sure enough all of the models had it, aiming right for us. Bulls eye.
這是一頭怪物，而牠正朝我們而來。
This is a monster, and it's coming.
在家裡中來來回回，把東西往上堆。
Walk through the house a few times, putting things up, you know.
把我尼泊爾的地毯放在櫃子上，然後吉他…
My silk rug from Nepal up on the top shelf, and my guitar,
反正就是之類的事情。
I mean, you know, you just do these things, you know.
另外一個作法應該是，東西全部帶走、閃人，
I mean another way to do that is get all you stuff and go, that's option 1,
這應該才是最佳解。我卻沒有這樣做。
probably the best option. I didn't grow up in that option.
Alvin去接了他84歲的爸爸回家，
Alvin collected his 84-year-old father
然後在颶風來臨時，把他們自己緊緊關在屋內。
than barricaded the two of theminside this house as the hurricane approached.
你睜大雙眼瞪著大自然，她通常都是好端端的。
You stare Mother Nature in the eye, usually she's fairly benign.
然後她一路過來，不慌不忙，卻又殘酷無情。
And she comes along, methodically, ruthlessly.
最後她站在你面前要跟你拼個生死，你敢嗎?你敢嗎?
And then she stands toe to toe, and dares you, dares you.
去把你最好的裝配拿出來呀!去呀!來玩玩吧!
Go ahead and get your best equipment, now, go ahead, do it, let's dance.
我想我們對於把一些特別的事件歸因於全球暖化需要很謹慎。
I think ones got to be very careful about attaching a particular event to global warming.
儘管如此，颶風的強度和海水表面溫度有關，
But nevertheless the intensity of hurricanes is related to surface sea temperature,
所以越來越強的颶風的確和全球暖化有關聯。
so increased intensity of hurricane is associated with global warming.
天亮的時候，Alvin家的積水已經即胸，而且還在上升。
By first light, the water in Alvin's house is chest-deep and still rising.
所以他幫助他爸爸上船然後往沒淹水的地方駛去。
So he helped Alvin Sr. into their boat and headed for dry land.
那裡只有一艘船還浮著，發動一艘船也沒甚麼大不了，反正就發動了。
There's just one boat that's floating, so it's no big deal to launch the boat, it's launched.
真的甚麼地標都沒有。在樹高的位置行駛過你家附近，
There's no landmarks, really, to speak of, that's a real different perspective,
真的是很不一樣的觀點。
driving through your neighborhood at tree level.
然後你突然了解到，還有很多人都還在等待救援。
Then, all of a sudden you realize there is a lot of people who stayed behind.
那裡沒有海巡人員、沒有警察…
There's no coastguard or police or…
我們大部分的國民警衛隊都在世界的其他地方。伊拉克、阿富汗。
Most of our national guards were elsewhere in the world, Iraq, Afghanistan.
超過兩個漫長的整天裡，Alvin救了約200人和他們的寵物
Alvin rescued 200 people, and their pets, over 2 long days,
其中包括一個95歲的老人和一個六個星期大的嬰兒。
including a 95-year-old man and a six-week-old baby.
當那個小籃子被送出窗戶，是個很特別的時候。
that little basket came out of the window, that was a pretty special time.
他閉著眼睛，很平靜的，真是會讓你停下腳步，
And just as peaceful eyes-closed, it just stops you, in your tracks, dead stop,
深吸一口氣，你知道的，沒有甚麼比那更珍貴了。
take a breath, you know, there's nothing more precious than that.
Alvin的鄰居算是幸運的了，
Alvin's neighbors were the lucky ones,
卡崔納颶風是美國史上最嚴重的氣候災害。
hurricane Katrina was America's worst weather related event to that date.
而且不過是未來災難的冰山一角。
And it was just a taste of what was to come.
一些全球頂尖的科學家，經過多年的辯論，宣佈"的確是人類的錯"…
"It is our fault," after years of debate, some of the world's top scientists…
"無庸置疑"，是他們用來形容人類行為是…
"Unequivocable," this the word they used, human activity is…
造成地球氣候的改變，不再是一個可以辯論的議題。
Contributing to changes in our earth climate, and that issue is no longer up to debate.
在Andermatt，
In Andermatt,
他們用一種特殊的保護墊罩住冰山來減少它夏日的融化。
they've covered the glacier with a special protective sheet reduce its summer melt.
我為環境盡一份心力的方法是使用Ariel，並且把溫度調降到30度。
One way I do my bit for the environment is turning to 30 with Ariel.
這是為了補償我搭為了工作而搭飛機(對環境造成的傷害)。
This is offsetting all those flights that I take, that I have to for my job.
David Cameron甚至還穿用舊消防員長褲回收製成的鞋子。
David Cameron even wears recycled shoes made from old fireman's trousers.
儘管付出了一些努力在控制污染和對氣候的影響，
Despite all the efforts to control pollution and its effect in our climate,
溫室氣體的排放量卻屢創新高，更沒有下降的趨勢。
the level of greenhouse gas emission has reached a record highand shows no signs of being reversed.
儘管有京都議定書和一大堆要減少二氧化碳的言論，
Despite the Kyoto treaty, and all the talk of reducing emission of carbon dioxide,
這個對溫室效應影響最嚴重的氣體，排放的速度卻是越來越快。
level of this key greenhouse gas are rising faster than ever.
六點半，帶有涼意的秋天早晨。Alvin準備上班去，尋找更多石油。
06:30 am on a cool autumn morning, and Alvin's heading up to work, searching for more oil.
很諷刺的，劇風重創了紐奧良外海的產油建設。
Ironically, the oil infrastructure off the coast of New Orleans suffered major damage during the hurricane,
但殼牌動作很快，經過九個月的維修，
but Shell moved fast to carry out repair and just 9 months later,
油井開始產油，所有人回到工作岡位。
the rigs are online, and everyone's back at work.
石油是來自古老的海洋植物當時吸收陽光。
Oil was formed when ancient plant life in the ocean, absorbed energy from the ancient sun.
當這些植物死掉後，會和很多很多其他海洋生物的遺體一起沉積在海床中。
When these plants died, they settled in the ocean floor along with the dead bodies of tons and tons of ocean creatures.
幾千年以後，溫度上升使這些有機物質漸漸的改變，
Over millennia, temperature increased and the organic matter was gradually cooked
直到最後太陽的能量終於被儲存在石油裡。
until the sun's energy was stored inside oil.
一億五千萬年以後，殼牌的地質學家們分析石油到底藏在甚麼地方，
150 million years later, Shell's geologists analyzed where the oil might be,
然後鑽三英哩到海床下取出樣本。
and then drilled 3 miles down into the seabed to collect samples.
拿去吧，Al。謝啦
Hey you go Al, get yourself.  Thank you…
我們取得樣本並分析他們的化石含量。那些微觀的化石。
We get the samples and analyze them for the fossil contents. The microscopic fossils.
那其實就是另一個地質科學的方法，來幫我們增加找到油田的機率。
And it's just another geo-scientific tool in order to improve your possibility of finding oil.
在我看來，這麼說可能有點自大，
In my opinion, probably arrogantly so,
做這些事是個崇高的使命，
but it's pretty high calling actually to try to do that,
去了解或是參與時間的演進。
to try to figure out or maybe take apart, you know, time itself.
幾千年之前，
Go back a few thousand years,
每天日光照在地球表面產生的能量，限制了生產作物或是餵食動物的數量。
and the energy available to grow our crops or feed animals was limited by the daily sunlight falling on the earth.
但是現在，
But now,
我們每年貪婪的使用相當於遠古一百年才能蒐集到的太陽的能量。
we gorge ourselves on hundreds of years worth of sunlight every single year.
現代生活的每一部份幾乎都可說是從石油製成。
Every part of modern life is now literally made of oil.
從CD到塑膠袋，從藥品到電腦，
From CDs to plastic bags, to medicines and computers.
從衣服和地毯到髮膠到行動電話。
From clothes and carpets to hair gel and cell phones.
他用途廣的讓人驚訝。
It's a fantastically useful substance.
再來就是我們的食物，
Then there's our food,
1卡路里的食物從生產、包裝、冷藏到運送，大約需花80卡路里的石油
each calorie we eat used about 80 oil calories to produce, package, refrigerate and transport.
化石燃料還被加工製成肥料，使得大約2億人口得以生存下去。
And fossil fuel produce fertilizers now feed about 2 billion people who could not otherwise stay alive.
人類最好能夠利用剩下的石油，去打造一個不需要以靠石油過活的社會。
It would be wise for humanity to use the remaining oil to build the new society which could run without it.
但相反的，我們卻恣意的每天燃燒幾千萬桶的原油。
But we are, instead, indiscriminately burning tens of millions of barrels every day.
這些在大約40年後都會消失，後代子孫將一無所有。
It'll all be gone in about 40 years, leaving pretty much none for future generations.
然後你會看到他，聞到他，你知道的，
And then you see it, and you smell it, and, you know,
又油膩又醜，聞起來充滿錢的味道，如此美麗。
it's greasy and ugly and smell so much like money, it's just beautiful, you know.
在2005年為13億磅，也就是一小時一千五百萬磅，一秒鐘四百磅。
13 billion pounds in 2005, that's 1.5 million pounds an hour, 400 pounds a second.
有一大半的利益都是來自這裡，奈及利亞，
And a hefty chunk of those profits came from here, Nigeria,
然而那裡的人們每天只靠著不到一美元生活。
where most of the population lives on less than 1 dollar a day.
這是我們喝的水。
This is the water we drink.
裡面有很多青蛙、蟾蜍。
你可以在這裡找到所有的病菌。
用顯微鏡看的話，就可以看到裡面有會讓我們感染的病菌。
我們以為如果我們把殼牌引進來社區...
就能改變這裡的水質。
但狀況都還是一樣。
這是我們的醫療中心...
22歲的Layefa Malin志向是當一個醫生
22-year-old Layefa Malin has an ambition to trained as a doctor
並在自己的村落服務。
and then work in a home village called Cojabanee(??),
殼牌打算在這堳堣@座醫療中心。
where Shell started building this medical center.
三年來這裡都是像現在這樣。
但我們還是期望他們可以來這裡完成它。
就如同其他上百個在尼日三角洲附近的社區計畫，建設都被廢止了。
Like hundreds of other community projects across Niger delta, construction has been abandoned.
殼牌堅稱是因為害怕發生綁票事件。
Shell maintains that's because of the risk of kidnapping.
13%的石油獲利應該被使用於社區開發。
13% of the oil revenue is supposed to be spent on community development.
但當地居民應該分得的款項幾乎都被腐敗的政治系統污走。
But the local people share is almost all lost to the corrupt political system.
所以儘管身處西非石油獲利最高的區域，
So despite being in the most profitable oil region in West Africa,
Layefa的村落沒有醫療系統，沒有中等學校，沒有電，也沒有飲用水
Layefa's village has no health service, no secondary school, no electricity, and no drinking water.
我認為在2004年很多人死亡。
很多。
我記得應該有快20人。
大多是孩童。
甚至還有我媽媽的小孩，也就是我的妹妹...
也死了，死於霍亂。
我想我妹妹的死，讓我有了很大的動機。
想成為一個好醫生。
不只是個醫生，要是個好醫生。
我的傷寒就是經由水源傳染的。
我知道要當個醫學院學生要花很多錢。
我需要付住宿費還有其他東西。
然後我也想要穿好看的衣服。
這表示我要從今年開始捕魚...
一直到...可能四年吧。
Layefa，把你的槳放那邊。
把你的槳放到另一邊。
高壓油管，請勿下錨。
漁獲並不好。
因為油汙染水面，
殺死了大部分的魚。
我們甚至也補不到大魚了，只有些小魚而已。
快把網拉起來我們才可以走。
我們只抓了兩條魚。
有時候油會佈滿整隻魚。
還必須要拿Omo(一種清潔劑)洗。
新聞裡說
我們現在一天生產了幾十幾百萬桶的油。
但我們不但沒有變有錢，
反而越來越窮。
Layefa所描述的現象被稱作"資源的詛咒"。
Layefa is describing a phenomenon known as "the resource curse".
很不合常理的，發覺石油常使一個國家更為窮困。
Paradoxically, finding oil usually increases a country's poverty.
因為石油資源常被控制在極少數人的手中，
As the oil wealth is concentrated in hands of a few,
一個國家的農業、教育、醫療就會被忽略，甚至崩垮。
so the agriculture, education, and health system of the country become neglected and often collapsed.
天然氣日以繼夜的在尼日河三角洲燒著，
The local people health problems are compounded by gas flare,
加重了當地居民的健康問題。
burning nights and days throughout the Niger delta,
氣喘、支氣管炎、皮膚癌全都和這有關。
asthma, bronchitis, skin diseases, and cancer have all been linked.
天然氣會在石油附近找到，但是運輸上會有危險，
That gas is found alongside oil, but, as it's dangerous to transport,
所以很難賣到海外市場。它可以在奈及利亞當地用來烹飪或是加熱，
it can't easily be sold to over sea markets. It could be use for cooking and heating within Nigeria,
但建造這些基礎設施很花錢，所以石油公司就直切把天然氣燒掉。
but building infrastructure is expensive, so the oil company just burn it off.
這些火焰每年產生七千萬噸的二氧化碳，
Its flares emit about 70 million tons of carbon dioxide every year
相當於一千萬戶的倫敦家庭一年的排放量。
more than the annual emissions from 10 million British homes.
因為他們很有錢...
也是很強大的公司...
所以他們就為所欲為。
they just do whatever they like.
為什麼美國的城市設計使得每個人都一定需要有一部車?
Why are American cities designed so it's almost impossible not to have a car?
為什麼幾百條的鐵路，像紐約、
Why were a hundred railways in cities like New York,
費城、洛杉磯等，建造了以後又被故意破壞?
Philadelphia, and Los Angles bought up and then deliberately destroyed?
為什麼電動車會被廢棄?
Why do the electric cars get scrapped?
為什麼我們和澳洲
Why were we, along with Australia,
成為唯一兩個沒有簽署京都議定書的國家?
the only two countries not to sign the original Kyoto climate treaty?
為什麼石油公司的遊說者可以任意的修改政府對於全球暖化的報告?
Why was an oil company lobbyist allowed to change official government reports on global warming?
為什麼幫忙香菸產業宣傳抽菸很健康的同一家公關公司，
Why was the same PR firm employed by the tobacco industry to persuade the public that smoking is healthy,
又被石油產業請來宣傳氣候變遷的說法還有待商榷?
then employed by the oil industry to convince us there was still doubt about climate change?
不到1%的學界人士還在懷疑，全球暖化是否人類活動造成
而約60%的民眾仍相信這還有待商榷
替代能源已經存在超過50年了，為什麼我們很少使用?
Alternative energy has been available for 50 years, why have we barely used it?
為什麼白宮上的太陽能板被拆掉了?
Why were solar panels taking off the white house?
因為早從工業時代一開始，
Because right from the early days of the industry,
石油商人和那些看不見的利益就對我們的政府官員有很多"關照"
the oil men and their unseen profit have had an unhealthy influence on the people running our country.
而現在這些石油商人都是我們的政府官員。
And now, they all are the people running our country.
他們也提供資金。
And they're providing the cash, too.
石油產業不只是和政府有掛勾，
Oil business isn't just in bed with the government,
石油產業就是政府。
it is the government.
現在Layefa正前往一個附近的村落，
Here, Layefa is going to a nearby village,
Odiama，這裡之前曾被政府屠殺過。
Oiama, that was massacre by the government.
這個村落曾經因為一塊土地的所有權問題而挑起了紛爭，
The village was involved in a dispute about ownership of a piece of land,
一塊殼牌打算鑽油井的土地。
on which Shell planed to drill for oil.
政府宣稱這個村落藏匿了許多恐怖分子，
The government claimed that the village was harboring terrorists,
當政府派軍進入的時候，
and when they sent the military in to find those terrorists,
遭到村民的開槍攻擊。
the villagers opened fire on the soldiers.
Layefa要去聽聽來自Omiekma Wekid敘述，了解從村民角度的看法。
Layefa has gone to hear the villagers' side of the story, from Omiekma Wekid
14艘快艇過來。
上面都是軍人。
然後我們看到了四艘砲艇。
再來我們就聽到了"蹦"一聲，房子開始起火。
我們就說，"快逃吧"
整座島嶼都在搖晃。
這裡之前有座建築。
他們來這然後把他燒成灰燼。
有一個村民想要逃命，
一直跑跑跑，跑到森林裡去。
兩個小孩死在這裡。
我在森林裡待了兩的星期。
沒有食物。
摘些葉子。
就在這些灌木叢之後，你可以想像這潭水是怎麼樣子。
我們飲用這些水。
很多小孩都死了。
那時候我已經懷孕了。
但因為喝了這些骯髒的水，
在我把他生出來的時候，
他不停的上吐下瀉。
我就這麼失去他了。
國際特赦組織調查該屠殺案後表示，
Amnesty international investigated the massacre and concluded that,
雖然政府是造成傷亡的主因，
although the government was responsible for the killings,
殼牌也應該要確定他們的行為不會造成這個衝突發生。
Shell Nigeria should have made sure that their activities did not contribute to the conflict.
那些沒逃走的人，都被集中起來，毆打一頓。
強姦了一些女生。
這裡本來是我祖父的地方。
他和他的家人住在一起。
他們放火燒了他的家。
殺了他。
他們燒死他?
他們射殺他。
一些小小孩當躺在我們家中，
他們就燒死他們。
就連老先生老太太，
那些雙眼已盲的，
也被他們燒死了。
they burned them off.
人類歷史充滿了血腥暴力和一大堆值得偷竊的物品。
Human history is littered, with the corpses of people who had stuff worth stealing.
動物
Animals,
水源
water,
亮晶晶的東西
shinny things,
肥沃的土地
fertile land,
香料
spices.
Hmm! 豆蔻片。要茶嗎?
Hmm! Nutmeg slice, tea?
提到有甚麼東西值得偷一下，有一洲甚麼東西都有，
But when it came to stuff worth pinching one continent had it all,
象牙、銅、棉花、橡膠、木材、錫、金、鑽石、還有人。
ivory, copper, cotton, rubber, wood, tin, gold, diamonds, and people.
奴隸便宜又好用，
As cheap energy, slaves were unbeatable,
一直到發現比較"不麻煩"的能源之後，
until the less troublesome energy source was discovered,
才開啟了新時代。
and the new era began.
人類數量成長了五倍多。
Human numbers increased 5 times over.
因為每個人想要的東西越來越多，
And with each person wanting more and more stuff,
石油就成了兵家必爭的資源。
oil became "the resource" worth fighting for all around the world.
你知道到底為什麼我們要攻打伊拉克嗎?
Well, you want to know the real reason why to warn Iraq?
根據前美國聯邦儲備委員會Alan Greenspan的說法，很簡單，三個字母，
According to the former Federal Reserve chairman Alan Greenspan, it's a simple, 3 letter answer.
不是WMD(大規模傷害性武器)，是OIL。
Not WMD(Weapon of mass destruction), it's O-I-L.
要承認這件大家都已經知道，卻又不方便承認的事情，讓我感到難過，
那就是伊拉克戰爭的主因就是石油。
你上周末可能已經聽前殼牌總裁脫，
You might read the ex-chairman of Shell
當世界石油產量達到高峰，每桶石油可能來到超過150美元。
that said over weekend that oil can hit over 150 dollars a barrel as world production begins to peak,
這是的確一個壞消息，特別是對於一個整個經濟，
not really good news for a country whose entire economy,
甚至整體生活方式，
not to mention its entire way of life,
都靠著便宜的石油在過活的國家。
is based on cheap oil.
約旦，安曼
我們因為戰爭來到這裡。
我們不停的想試著...
跨過邊境...
但他們不斷的把我們送回伊拉克。
我們最後終於過來了。
我們來到這裡的時候非常高興。
我們租下這個地方。
我們爸爸有頭顱子。
我們之前都會騎著牠。
我很害怕...
當牠跑很快的時候。
但當美國人來的時候...
在三更半夜裡...
我們必須要逃跑。
因為我們覺得...
他們會殺了我們。
隔天早上我們回去的時候...
我們發現我們的驢子已經死了...
我爸是全伊拉克裡最好的。
但後來美國人一來...
...就殺了他。
早上我們發現他已經死了。
我只希望他沒死。
我還是不敢相信他們殺了他。
人類歷史上，
我們把世界帶往更美好的方向，
we left the world in a better place,
這就是進步，
then we found it, that was progress,
輪子，律法，抗生素，
the wheel, rule of law, penicillin.
這就是我們對我們子孫的承諾。
It was our covenant to our children, grandchildren;
我的孩子們因為我背棄了承諾而生氣，
my children went angry with me for breaking the covenant,
他們拼了命只想存活下來而懶得去怪罪能源的浪費，
they were too busy trying to stay alive to waste energy on blame,
透過暴動、難民營和社會的崩潰才得以生存。
trying to negotiate their way through food riots, refugee camps, and the collapse of society.
而我的孫子們應該也會感到生氣，
But I think my grandchildren would have been angry,
如果他們有幸能長大成人的話。
had they survived into adulthood.
嗨，阿祖。
嗨，Jean。
給我親一下。
我們這一代造成了這些問題。
總是想到進步、進步、進步。
只會要求越來越多，
壓榨我們的地球。
看，鹿的足跡耶。
我父母見證了汽車和飛機問世。
現在的小孩需要有自己的汽車才可以出們上學。
很快的...
他們就會比我們進步許多。
因為他們多擁有了許多東西。
從電視上看得更多
但這不代表他們就比較快樂。
當我們年輕的時候，
家裡並沒有自來水。
我們需要出去取水，
這也讓我們使用的時候更謹慎。
同理用電也是一樣。
今天有陽光，是晴天，
我們就不開電燈。
我們父母這樣教導我們，
但我們卻沒有想要這樣教導我們的孩子。
在沙漠滑雪，
Skiing in desserts,
拼命開暖氣，
heating the air,
照亮空盪盪的辦公室，
lighting empty offices,
能源便宜的荒謬，就經濟的角度看起來，根本就可以忽略不計。
energy is so ridiculously cheap, it makes perfect economic sense to just pick it away.
中國是新的壞人，因為他們每四天就蓋一座新發電廠。
China is new bad guy, because they're building a new power station every 4 days.
新電廠四分之一的能量被用來製造供給我們的東西。
But the quarter of that energy makes stuffs for us.
西方公司付給中國勞工很鳥的薪水，讓他們製造一些很鳥的塑膠玩具，
Western company pay Chinese workers crap wages to make crap plastic toys,
然後運到歐洲，再用更多塑膠包裝起來。
then ship them to Europe, and wrap them in more plastic.
人們開著他們的吃油怪物到城外的大賣場。
Punters drive to the out-of-town megastore in their gas-guzzlers.
塑膠玩具和塑膠盒子被裝進塑膠袋子。
Plastic toy and plastic box goes into plastic bag.
兩天後玩具壞了，
2 days later, toy broken,
又被運回去中國的掩埋場。在那堳袡L…大概5萬年的餘生吧。
and back it goes to a Chinese landfill where it stays for about, hmm, 50 thousand years?
瓶裝水比水龍頭水屌，
Water from the bottle's much better than the tap.
瓶裝水來自...高山泉水...甚麼甚麼鳥...的好地方。
...... Mountain spring spot.
多耗費了800倍的能源，
800 times more energy wasted
還貴上10,000倍，
and 10,000 times more expensive for you.
很弔詭的抉擇吧?
It's a tricky decision.
我在 63 年還 65 年的時候建造了我的房子，
當時他們在建造白朗峰隧道。
我們一開始不太在意，
但我們讓自己
逐漸被車潮吞噬。
貨車緊接而來。
一開始只有小貓兩三隻，
但他們現在把道路拓寬成四線道，
以容納四五千輛卡車
每天行經這段道路。
一個馬鈴薯。
兩個馬鈴薯。
三個。
四、五。
六。
結束。
越來越多來自北方的車，
載著馬鈴薯。
他們穿過隧道，
去義大利清洗。
遠在天邊的義大利。
然後加工成馬鈴薯泥再運回來。
牛奶也是一樣。
他們將牛奶運送出去以製成優格。
再運回來。
真的是瘋了，瘋了。
美國人並不喜歡我們。
我們穿著我們的鞋子直到它裂成兩半。
但他們的鞋子只要出了一點小狀況，
他們就會把他丟了。
美國人、英國人，全部都一樣。
他們的舊鞋子會...
被裝在大箱子裡送來這邊。
我們買下它們，修理之後，
再賣掉。
我們有個哥哥，Malik。
當開始轟炸的時候，
有一架飛機掠過他上頭。
他當時穿著尼龍材料的衣服，
伊拉克，巴格達。
所以當他身上著火的時候，
他受傷的非常嚴重。
他的衣服黏在他身上，將他皮膚撕下來。
我們分批來到約旦。
我們大部份的人都來了。
但Malik被攔了下來，並被送回伊拉克。
他們遣返他八次。
如果Malik過來，
沒有電話的話，
我發誓我會把我的給他。
然後他可以星期五過來幫忙修鞋。
幫我一下。
來呀。
如果我看到美國人的話，我會殺了他們。
因為他們殺了我爸。
嘿!
下去!
我不想。
我是 Al Jazeera。
Call in請撥007845。
注意，我是 Al Jazeera。
你們可以贏得四輛悍馬。
和四部SUV。
很多不同的思想都想要稱霸全世界，
Lots of ideas have tried to take over the world,
但獲勝的只有一個。
but there's only one winner.
(消費主義)
3000多個廣告每天轟炸我們，
3000 adverts bombard us every day.
告訴我們如果有漂亮的肌膚，就可以更迷人、更快樂，
Telling us we'll be happier, more atracttive with better skin,
只要我們肯買他們的產品的話。
if only we buy their product.
為了讓顧客們可以拼命噴錢，
To get there,
他們創造了一堆誘因，和欲求不滿的心理。
they create incentives and insatiable desire to buy more and more stuff.
美國人為此"奮鬥"了最久，
Americans have been advertised that longest,
他們現在平均一個人耗費的能源等於兩個歐洲人，
and they now each consumed twice as much energy as an European,
九個中國人，
9 times more than a Chinese person,
十五個印度人，
15 times more than an Indian,
五十個肯亞人。
and 50 times more than someone from Kenya.
如果地球上65億人口都像歐洲人或日本人一樣的消費的話，
If all the 65 billion here on earth consumed like European or Japanese,
我們需要另外兩個地球這麼多的資源。
we need two more planets worth of resources.
如果都像美國人或是澳洲人或是加拿大人一樣的消費的話，
If everyone consumed like American or Australian and Canadian,
我們需要四個地球。
we need another four.
當2040年，達到90億人口的時候，
And in 2040 or so when there are about 90 billion of us,
又要再另外加兩個地球。
we need two more again.
帝國主義唯一的目標就是不斷的擴張，
Capitalism's only goal is ever expending growth,
但在不會擴張地球上不斷的擴張…
but ever expending growth on just a one not expending planet…
不可能!
It's impossible.
偽善的經濟體系後果就是災難，
The con economic system is disastrous,
不只是對地球，也同時是對大多數的人。
not just for the planet, but for most people, too.
400年的帝國主義，讓最有錢的1%分得40%的財富，
400 years of capitalism has allowed the richest one 1% to take 40% for themselves,
只剩下1%給最窮的人。
leaving just 1% for the poorest to have.
每次有人想要擁有不同的生活都是癡人說夢。
But anyone wanting to live differently is fool ticket every time.
因為利益被當作唯一衡量的標準，
With profit, the only measuring step,
殘害地球的行為隨之而來，
destroying the planet is written into the system,
氣候變遷開始失控也沒甚麼好意外的。
and run away climate change is not very surprising result.
Logo重要的就是顏色，像淺灰色，
The logo effectively is color, you know, light grey, you know,
Orange Telecom那樣，他們就是橘黑色。
orange telecom, they are orangey black.
我們的Logo是明亮的顏色。
Our logo is fluorescent color.
當經濟每分每秒都在改變的時候，我們投入了這個戰場
Where everything changes in economy in minute, you have an airline moving in.
使人們可以更快的從事各種商業活動，
Because people can basically do business alot faster,
加快這個速度，也就表示人們有更多的可支配收入。
if businesses grow a lot faster, people have more disposable income,
再來消費主義就來參一腳，
then, you know, consumerism sets in,
消費主義來參一咖，就可以使社會進步，
and you know where the verge where base consumerism is setting in,
就像美國一樣。
just moving a lot like America.
我過著這樣的生或一點也不高興。
我現在23歲了，應該身在更好的地方才對。
我一直想要去類似...
美國這種地方。
住在棟舒適的房子裡。
擁有很炫的車子。
飲用好的水。
吃好吃的東西。
我一直希望我們的人民...
至少我身邊的人和我自己...
可以過那樣的生活。
那種美麗的生活。
如果能過著那樣的生活，那根本就不會想要死。
你只想要永遠活在世界上。
Jeh現在前往位於法國的空中巴士總部，
Here, Jeh travels to Airbus headquarter in France,
因為他們將要在他開業3年內提供26架飛機給他。
as they'll be supplying him with 26 planes in his first 3 years.
印度境內只有200架民航機，而中國有800架。
We have only 200 aircrafts commercially flying in India, China has 800.
要追上中國、歐洲，
Ultimately, you know, we have a very long way to go,
是一條長遠的路。
playing catch up with China, catch up with Europe,
舉例來說，美國的西南航空，有417架飛機，
or, you know, say, America one airline, South West, has 417 aircrafts.
比整個印度多上一倍。
That's double the amount of aircrafts we have as a country.
你知道，有一句簡單的話道出了我的想法，
You know, we simple sentence for me, summarizes it all.
就是事情會越來越好。
Thing is gonna get better.
我的房子裡，有10呎深的積水混著爛泥，
In my main house, is has 10 feet of water in it,
整整泡了3個禮拜。
marinated in that sludge for 3 weeks, almost.
所以現在的狀況就是全毀了。
So it's current state of my house, it's been demolished.
有用的財產，就是一片土地，等著在上面蓋一棟新房子。
It's flat piece of a property waiting for another house to go on that.
我失去了所有東西，我所有的東西，
I lost everything, everything that i owned,
從傳家遺物到廚房的衛生紙之類的所有所有東西，
I mean everything from family heirlooms to the paper towels sitting on your kitchen counter,
都失去了。
in everything in between, it goes on and on.
有兩個超級，超級水的橡樹存活下來了，
Two beautiful, beautiful oak trees I did not lose,
就是那種原生、土生土長、維吉尼亞的橡樹，
you know, local, indigenous, quikes, virginianas, live oaks
枝條成蔭，超級超級水。
that sprawl all over the place, beautiful, beautiful things.
這些就是我僅存的，兩棵橡樹和一片空蕩蕩的草坪，其他的都沒了。
That's what I have left, two old oak trees and an empty lawn, everything else is gone.
糟透了。
That sucks.
失去所有的東西，讓人無法承受。
Losing everything you have, it's so overwhelming.
伴隨而來的傷痛更是影響深遠。
And the grief that comes with that, it is just profound.
我們很有默契的一起假裝氣候變遷沒有發生，
We have an unspoken collected pact to pretend climate change wasn't happening,
好像我們只要用力的忽略他，就真的不會成真。
as though as long we ignore it hard enough, It wouldn't be true.
但不是每個人都這樣，有一些人在大聲疾呼。
Not absolutely everyone, a few were shouting fire.
嗨，進來吧。
Hello, come on in.
面對氣候變遷最大的困難是，
One of the greatest difficulties with climate change
我們今天的排放可能會在30到40年後才會對溫度有影響，
is that the effects of our emissions today are not actually realized in terms of the temperature
所以是個"時間延遲"的系統。
for 30 or 40 years so there is this time-lag system.
這對人類就很棘手，
Which makes it difficult for us, humans, to respond
因為我們經過演化的結果，就是只會立即的威脅有反應，
because we're evolutionary equipped to deal with the very immediate threats
像是大軍壓境或是危險的動物。
like advancing armies or dangerous animals.
對於長期的問題，我們就不知如何正確的應對，就像氣候變遷這種。
We're not so well-equipped with dealing rationally with very long term problems like climate change.
所以我們現在就必須有所作為以防範未然，
So we have to act now to stop something happening in the future,
如果我們真的要等到氣溫已經完全改變再做事，
if we wait until the full temperature effects are already upon us,
一切就太晚了。
then it's far too late to stop.
記住一個比甚麼都重要的數字，
If you remember one single number above all else,
2度。
make it two degrees,
現在幾乎全世界，
now everyone in the world pretty much,
像歐盟、大型跨國企業、綠色和平組織、政黨，
the European Union, big multi-national corporations, Greenpeace, political parties,
都同意我們必須防止全球氣溫相較於工業革命前上升超過2度，
all agreed that we have to stabilize global temperatures within 2 degrees above pre-industrial level,
原因是，超過這個臨界點，就這個這麼狹窄的界線，
and the reason for that is because, if you cross that threshold, the narrow tipping point in the earth system,
暖化的過程就會完全的失控。
which could drive the warming process essentially out of control.
世界上大量的碳都會釋出，
Huge amount of carbon could be coming out of the world,
樹木和土壤，西伯利亞永凍層的甲烷也會跑出來，
trees and soils, methane could be coming out of the perma-frost in Siberia
這些多出來進入大氣層的溫室氣體，
and it's that extra input of greenhouse gases into the atmosphere,
會導致最糟糕的狀況發生，地球上的溫度上升6度或更多，
which then leads us up to the worst case scenario to 6 or more degrees
最終大部分的生命將會滅絕。
and the eventual wipeout of most of the life on earth.
能源排放從差不多1950開始不斷上升。
So power emission has been going up, between, let's says, 1950,
現在我們必須要讓上升減緩，穩定，
and now they need to level out, stabilize, and then decline
然後盡快下降到一個可以維持恆定的水平，差不多在2050年削減80%。
just as rapidly to sustainable levels about an 80% cut by 2050.
重要的是，想要使溫度上升幅度在2度之內，
But crucially, to keep the temperature rise within 2 degrees,
在2015年這個值就必須達到穩定。
this point of stabilization need to be at around 2015.
意思就是，真的，我們擁有的時間一分一秒的過去，
And so that means, really, the time, timeline we've got, ticking clock,
從現在2008算起來，7年之內我們就要讓全球排放穩定下來。
is that we have to stabilize global emission within just 7 years from now as we speak 2008.
讓整個人類文明轉型成低碳的經濟，
And scale of this task to achieve a transformation to a low carbon economy
這個任務的規模很巨大，
of the entire, entirety of human civilization,
很重要，可能是人類有史以來最重大的。
is obviously, is huge, monumental task, probably the greatest humanity ever faced.
還記得跑去看冰河的倫敦一家人嗎?
Remember the English family who went to see the glacier?
他們現在位在英國西南方的家鄉，Cornwall，
They're back home in Cornwall, south west England,
開始面對處理他們自己浪費能源的問題。
inspire to start tackling their own energy wasting.
上面說英國平均一個人每年排放10噸的溫室氣體。
It says that the average Individual in the UK responsible for emitting 10 tons of greenhouse gas a year.
他們再計算現在他們一家到底排放出多少溫室氣體，
They're calculating exactly how much climate-change-gases their family currently produces,
並且該怎麼減量。
and how it can be reduced.
對，但那是一個人平均而已，我們有五個人。
Yeah, but that's the average individual, there are five of us.
恩…，不管怎麼看，都不太好。
Whichever way you look at this, it isn't good.
我們生產大約一半我們所需的食物，並減少對肉類和乳類的需求。
We produce about half of our food, and we try keep our consumption of meat and dairy down.
我的車是用雞脂肪當油，我們也盡量騎腳踏車。
My car runs on chick fat and we do cycle when we can.
我們剛買了風力發電機，足以生產我們全部的用電量。
We just got our wind turbine, which will produce all our own electricity.
我們的目標是每人每年降到剩一噸排放量，
We're aiming to cut down to about one ton each per year,
也就是地球上的樹木和植物可以再吸收的負荷量。
which is apparently the sustainable amount that the world's trees and plants can reabsorb.
但最大的問題是搭飛機，一個中程的旅行，像倫敦到紐約，
But the big problem is flying, just one mid-term flight, say, London to New York,
就可以讓3.5年的碳排放預算暴表。
would blow our entire carbon budget for about 3.5 years.
很明顯的，除了放火燒森林之外，
Apparently, other than setting fire to a forest,
一個人最能影響氣候變方式就是搭飛機。
flying is the single worst thing an ordinary individual can do to cause climate change.
真是有點讓人進退兩難，因為才剛有人邀我們去法國滑雪。
So, it's a bit of a dilemma, because we've just been invited to go skiing in France.
我們可以搭差不多40分鐘車到離這邊最近的機場Newquay上飛機，
Then I am flying from Newquay, which is our nearest airport,
say, 40 minutes from here, to Bergerac,
然後差不多一個多小時就可以飛到Bergerac。
which is like, you know, an hour and a half or something, from it.
意思就是我們可以早上從Cornwall出發，
And literally we could leave here in the morning, that's we leave like in, Cornwall,
we could leave Cornwall in the morning,
然後在午餐時間附近到Bergerac。
and be in Bergerac by sort of, for lunch, after lunch.
但如果你這樣想，這會為人類帶來災難，真實的災難，
But if you actually think, this is going to cause the death of people,  actually in effect
人類在為毀滅鋪路，就是個很恐怖的想法。
people are make that direct connection, then it's a really scary thought.
當然，如果我們要不要飛去法國，實在也都很難說，到底有沒有辦法解決問題。
Obviously, us not flying to France or not flying, wherever, it's hard to guess, will solve the problem.
但如果你想這麼做是正確的話，那很讓人沮喪。
But it's down to what you think it's the correct thing to do.
因為其他人都這麼作，而這不是做一件事的好理由。
Because everyone else's doing it, I mean, that is not a good reason to do anything.
回頭看歷史上後來讓人感到後悔的悲劇，
You know, to look at the terrible things in our history that everyone regrets now,
像大屠殺，各種慘案...很多之類的事，
you know, massacres, the holocaust…etc. a lot of that ,
都只不過是跟著當時的主流思想在走。
was just going a long way what was the predominant thinking at the time.
我一度有忌妒的感覺，
I almost jealous at the time,
要是在5年、10年前，我就會絲毫沒有罪惡感的跳上飛機，
5 or 10 years ago when I could just jump on a plane with impunity,
想都不用想，超爽ㄉ，不需要面對這種道德的困境。
I didn't even think about it, it's blissful, no moral dilemma there, whatsoever.
不用說，他們沒去搭飛機。
Needless to say, they didn't take that flight.
用參加對抗氣候變遷的遊行
And joining the climate change protest march
來慶祝結婚十周年紀念日應該不是大家都會做的，
may not be everybody's idea of the 10th wedding anniversary,
但這是Piers和Lisa從一開始認識就有同樣的理想。
but Piers and Lisa have share ideals from the moment they met.
我跟我朋友一起去參加派對，
My friend, we went along to the party together,
他基本上就是直接帶我去找Piers，說
and she just basically took me straight over to Piers and said,
"嘿，Piers，她是Lisa"，然後說，"答答答答嘟嘟嘟嘟答答答"
"Hey, look," you know "Piers, this is Lisa." And, dah dah dah …
就是這樣耶，就是這樣。我們就是…
And that was it, that was it. We just...
我們花了一整晚在聊風力發電機。
and spent the whole evening talking about wind turbines.
Piers在非洲、美洲、英國開發風力發電廠已經超過15年。
Piers has been developing wind farms in Africa, America, and Britain for over 15 years.
但他知道在急需重整的西方世界中，
But he knows that they only help slow the climate crisis
他對於減緩全球暖化貢獻，只佔了其中一小部分。
as a small part of a total reordering of western society.
還是有人覺得我們必須找到那麼一個解決法，
And there still is an idea that somehow we have to find the solution,
致勝的方式。
you know, the silver bullet.
不會有單一一種再生能源會是最終的解答，絕對不會。
No single renewable source is going to be the solution, absolutely not.
Piers也沒去想太多其他的選擇，
And Piers doesn't think much of the other option,
在此同時，大多數的人只是用手指比個十字架，
whereby everyone crosses their fingers
並希望某個奇蹟科技會及時出現。
and hopes that the miracle technology will be invented in time.
我不是說我們不應該開發其他東西，我們當然需要。
I'm not saying we shouldn't be developing other stuff, absolutely, we should be.
我們應該要盡我們所能。
We should be throwing everything after it.
但你要善用現在所擁有的。
But, you've got to make use of what's available now.
在英國，我們有很好的風力資源，
And in the UK, we've got a great wind resource,
我們就應該要咬緊牙關，努力達成目標。
and we just got to bite the bullet and go for it.
Piers提案在英國中部的Bedfordshire的Airfield Farm興建一座風力發電廠。
Piers has purposed a new wind farm as airfield farm at Airfield Farm in Bedfordshire, central England.
他可以在一年之類建造15作風力發電機供應13萬瓦的電力。
He could have 15 turbines installed and generating 13 megawatts of electricity within a year.
抗議氣球已經緩緩升空了，在此同時，讓我介紹一下我們身在何處。
Well, the process balloon is now going up, but while that's happening, I'll just explain where we are.
這裡是二次世界大戰轟炸機的基地...電話...****
This is the site of an old world war two bomber base... Phone...****
全部把大拇指比向下吧。
We all have our thumb down as well.
針對英國的調查顯示，70%~80%的人支持風力發電廠的概念。
UK-wise surveys point to about 70 ~ 80% in favor of wind farm as a concept.
困難的是，當在你家門口就有一座的話，
The difficulty is when you got one on your own doorstep,
就會生一種"只要不在我家就好"的病。
and then there is the sort of "not-in-my-backyard" syndrome.
Jim，是甚麼問題?
Jim, what's the problem?
問題真的是，這裡真的是英國風最小的一個地方。
The problem really is that this is one of the least windy sites in the country.
我希望明天不要風太大，不然它可能會纏繞在教堂上。
I hope it's not gonna get too windy tomorrow, and it wraps itself around the church.
恩…，我住在Coddington，而我們將會被這些很高的地衣包圍。
Well, I live in Coddington, and we're going to be absolutely surrounded by these high moss.
他們會擋住風景。
They're going to obliterate the view.
對於風力發電廠的質疑最後一定都有美觀的問題。
What it normally always comes down to with wind farms is the aesthetics, you know.
所有的大小爭議集結起來都是為了要對付這個終極的目標，
Everything else is basically put together to try and back up the ultimate thing,
而終極的目標就是，他們不要讓景觀變醜。
the ultimate thing is they don't want to spoil their view.
但我也有點擔心那輕微的噪音。
But I'm bit concern about the low level noise as well.
這個風力發電廠緊鄰於世界知名的直線加速賽車場SantaPod。
The wind farm site is right next to world famous Santa Pod drag-racing strip.
你問每一個人，沒有人會反對風力能源，這是重點。
Anybody you ask it, nobody's against wind energy, that's the point,
主要是反對不恰當使用風力能源。
t's against inappropriate wind energy use.
太催眠了，當你一個人開車，看到這些風車在轉動，
Hypnotic, you're driving alone, and you tend to saw this sails revolving,
會沒辦法專心開車。
and you're not concentrating on the driving.
Ernie_Braddock會因為有風力發電機設置在他的農場而得到利益，
Eurney Braddock will benefit financially having turbine on his farm,
但他跟鄰居Victoria Reeves起了一點紛爭。
but now he's in conflict with his neighbor, Victoria Reeves.
每個人都對此都很不爽，我們的地產將會貶值，
Well, everyone is very unhappy about it, we're gonna lose the value of our properties,
我們也沒辦法好好睡覺，它會造成改變。你根本就不明瞭，相信我。
we are not going to be able to sleep, it will make a difference, Eurney you have no idea, believe me.
根據Victoria的說法，
According to Victoria,
他們制止在蘇格蘭的另外一塊他們的地產上建造風力發電廠。
they stop to wind farm up in Scotland on the other estate in Scotland.
在90年代中期這是一個大勝利。
Back in the mid-90's that was a great victory.
"你不能依靠風力，它只能提供…",  "它是添加的…"
"It can't rely on the wind, it can only deliver… ", "It's an additive."
"添加的?你的意思是額外的嗎?對，他是額外的。", "這麼說吧，他是個經濟資源。"
"Additive? Do you mean additional? Yes, it is additional.", "It's a economics resources, put it that way. "
"不，Ernie，它不是。", "它是呀，它是呀。", "它跟那個無關，相信我。"
"No, Eurney, it doesn't. It's got to, it's got to. It does nothing of the sort, believe me. "
這是個義氣之爭，主要是來自恐懼，坦白講都是奠基於一堆狗屁。
It's an emotional campaign, it's about fear, mostly based on complete BS, frankly.
不過算了，事實勝於雄辯。
But never mind, facts are not a problem, you know.
"這是一個利益的戰爭，我希望你輸。", "好吧。"
"It's a fair fight, and I hope you lose.", "Alright."
現在是2005年的8月，就在孟買最嚴重的水災剛過不久，
This is august 2005, just after Mumbai's worst ever floods.
離Jeh的公司的第一個航班只剩幾個月。
And a couple of months before Jeh's first flight.
讓爸爸看一下你怎麼騎的，給爸爸看你可以騎多快。
Show daddy how good you ride this, show daddy how fast you can go, come on.
喔…不要再按了，他是吃電的。
Wooo... No more pushing, it's battery operated.
"我也沒辦法解決", "嘿，阿公耶"
"So, I can't finish either." "Hey, grandpa..."
Jeh是印度商業界最有錢最有權威的家族的後代。
Jeh is descended from one of India's richest, and most powerful business dynasties.
他們從18世紀的造船業到21世紀網際網路，都是最早搶占市場的。
They pioneered everything from ship building from the 18 centuries to internet services in the 21st.
他生長環境的特權帶給他廉價航空這個想法。
And around about way, his privileged up bringing sparked the idea for the low cost airline.
你想要我做甚麼?我要去機場了。
What do you want me to do? I'm going to the airport.
我的成長的過程，特別是年輕的時候，
Throughout basically my life, at young age,
我都會和一大堆僕人的小孩混在一起。你知道，就之類的。
I mean, I used to hang out with tons of, you know, servants' kids. You know, that sort of stuff.
當你回家的時候，突然會想，
You know, and when you go home,you say..., you suddenly think,
為什麼我擁有這麼多，而他們卻甚麼都沒有。
why do I have so much, and these guys have nothing.
而那造成了…不停的累積累積…
And that sort of…, and that constantly… adding up.
每個人在世上都有一個目標。
You know, everyone is here for a purpose.
而你應該要去了解你的最高目標是甚麼，進一步的去實現它。
The idea is to realize what your higher purpose is, and then realize how you gonna fulfill it.
最終我了解到我的目標是甚麼，
And eventually I realize what my higher purpose was,
就是我想要斬除貧窮。
it was to insure that I eradicated poverty.
Jeh志願在一個幫助村民遠裡窮困的慈善機構貢獻己力。
Jeh volunteers at the charity which helps villagers lift themselves out of poverty.
但就算動用了私人飛機、吉普車，
But even by private jet and jeep,
都還是一趟5個小時，900公里的旅程。
it's a 5 hour, 900 kilometers journey.
雇用私人飛機的花費跟花在村莊的費用一樣多，
Hiring a private jet is basically in terms of costs as much as the village does,
你知道，把村莊從平均以下拉到平均之上。
you know, take a village from below the poverty and put it above the poverty.
所以也算是達成目標了。
So effectively, in terms of it defeats the purpose.
所以我想說，試試看火車吧，從孟買需花大約26個小時，
And therefore I decided to, you know.. try the trains, from Bombay takes about 26 hours.
我對自己說，"哇，太誇張了"，
I said to myself, "wow, this is incredible."
人們可是付了不少錢，居然還要忍受這種垃圾般的東西。
You know, people pay good money and still have to basically put with this rubbish.
印度每天有一千五百萬人次搭乘火車。
15 million people travel by trains in India every single day.
Jeh的夢想就是讓他們離開火車，翱翔天際。
Jeh's dream is to get them all off the trains and into the skies.
我們現在不是處於戰爭。這並不是戰爭。
We're not at war at the moment. It's not a war.
但如果人們真的可以正確的了解當今到底發生了甚麼，
But people actually recognize that full implications of what's in store for us,
那他們就會把它當作戰爭了。
they would be treating it like a war.
如果有任何人把Airfield Farm當作例子，
If anybody takes Airfield Farm for example,
我的意思是這裡之前就是空軍基地，
I mean that was the year it was airbase,
有人從這裡起飛就再也沒活著回來。
people flew out there and died.
當然那是當時重大的事情，全球的問題，才讓大家赴湯蹈火。
Or of course, which was massive at the time, the global problem, and we have ourselves out.
真正的全球問題就需要這種程度的犧牲奉獻。
A real global problem that needs that kind of level of commitment.
要檢視的話，有許多許多其它的工業應該要被排在航空業前面。
There are many, many other industries that need to be looked in to first, before aviation.
選定一個工業當作攻擊目標也沒有甚麼不對，
it's not questionable choosing one industry to target,
畢竟最終我們每個人都應該為排放溫室氣體負責，
in ultimate deal, we all contribute to to to greenhouse gases,
都應該要為我們當前地球的危機負責。
we all contribute to the crisis that we have today with the planet.
所以最終確定我們的地球的安全與存亡是每一個人的任務。
So ultimately, in terms of, you know...
insuring our planet is safe and healthy is each one's job, task.
不管你是怎麼作的，例如少用一點衛生紙，
Whether you do it in your own way by using less tissue paper,
少用一點紙，就少一點樹被砍伐，買環保車或少搭飛機。
using less papers, less trees cut, buying green cars or not flying.
很明顯的，如果你不去做，需求就下降，
Obviously, if you're not doing it, and the demand goes down,
需求下降，供應就減少。
the demand goes down, the supply goes down.
生活就是需求和供給，或是供給與需求。
Life is about demand and supply, or supply and demand.
我們現在沒辦法補到這麼多魚了。
所以我決定從事另外一個行業。
就是柴油交易。
如此才能快速籌到我上大學的經費。
現在，因為石油稀少，
大部分的加油站，
都關門大吉了，
因為沒油可賣。
所以人們轉而向黑市購買。
來這裡買柴油。
我每星期三會去買柴油。
我將柴油轉賣給Rebecca太太。
她再賣給他的客戶。
我不想知道他們是誰。
我只知道她將石油再賣給客戶。
這樣壓力很大。
但因為有比較大的利益，
相較於捕魚。
好奇怪。看到這些影片片段。
Strange. Watching this film fragment.
像透過望遠鏡，觀察在遙遠海灘的人們。
Like looking through binoculars, observing people of far of beach.
他們不停的在追逐嬉鬧，對腳下踩的沙地繼續迷戀著，
Running around in circle, fixated on the small area of sand under their feet.
就算海嘯將要席捲而來。
As a tsunami races toward the shore.
Alvin，經過在石油公司工作三十年，他才剛開始過退休生涯。
Here's Alvin. He's just taken early retirement after thirty years on the oil industry salary.
他計畫利用晚年歲月享受大自然。
And he's planning to spend his later years outside enjoying nature.
喔，我當然是生態學家，跟一個環保人士
Oh, certainly I'm ecologist, and an environmentalist.
我完全知道
I really don't have a problem squaring that...
為石油公司工作讓我覺得...
Working for an oil company that I feel... has...
做得很不錯，並且也對環境有益。
done a pretty good job and in being environmentally friendly.
我開始在石油產業工作時，大約是七零年代中，
When I started working in the oil industries, about the mid 70's,
做為一個大學畢業的科學家，這是一條康莊大道。
it was clear path for me, as a scientist coming up college
我不大清楚石油產業內部的詳細狀況，那些利或弊之類的。
And I didn't know the detail of what goes on in the oil industry, the goods and the bad.
但每個產業的確都有那些， 利或弊。
But indeed every industry has that, goods and bad.
知道了這些事情的話，我還會再做嗎? 我當然會再做。
Would I do it again, knowing what I know now, of course I would do it again,
我的意思是，你必須要工作，一定需要做些事情。
I mean, you need to work, you need to do something
如果Airfield的風力發電廠繼續進行的話，
當地民眾會去把它毀了。
它會被摧毀的。
他將沒辦法提共任何電力。
了解嗎?
會有直接的行動來制止它的，
這樣你應該會知難而退了吧，
對吧?
我們有一個團體可以確保
風力發電廠會被完全摧毀。
我遇過最慘的例子是在一個展覽場，
The worst example I've had is a lady,
一個女的，一個有年紀的女士向我走來。
an old lady came up to me, at the public exhibition.
給了我一張從剪報，上面是一個男人被槍殺的圖片。
And gave me a cutting from a newspaper, with a picture of guy being shot
當地的反對運動是其中一個主因，
Local anti-campaign is one of the key factors,
他們推翻了英國百分之八十的風力發電計劃。
stopping about 80% of the proposed wind energy project in Britain.
如果這些計畫都實行的話，現在我們百分之十的電力會是零污染的。
Had they all been built, 10% of our Electricity would've been non-polluted.
他媽的，我們該怎麼說服印度跟中國，
How the heck are we meant to persuade people in India and China
我們該怎麼說服別人要去作到永續經營，
that they should develop in a more sustainable way when we are not prepared to even to accept
當我們連最基本的風力發電都沒辦法接受。
you know, the old wind farming landscape.
"結果怎麼樣?", "還不錯囉"
"So how's it going?", "All right, yes."
"沒遇到太多麻煩吧?", "沒什麼，至少沒有人來揍我"
"Not too much trouble?", "Not really, no, nobody's punched me up."
Piers回到了Ernie的農場，
Pierce has come back to the Ernie's farm
並且打算將風力發電機變得沒這麼顯眼。
with a plan to make the turbine less visible.
試著開始去推動讓那些讓反對人士耽擱了十八個月的計劃程序
Trying to kick start the planning process
that the anti-campaign has now held up for eighteen months.
又是十八個月的氣候變遷
Another eighteen months of climate change
又是十八個月，而我卻莫可奈何。
Another eighteen months, where I'm able to do nothing about it.
對 ，我真的真的覺得很X。
Yeah, I feel really ,really *** off for this.
你一定跟我有一樣的感覺，就是...，我們還是多少時間...
You must be feeling the same as me. It just, I mean how long have we got...
Piers妥協讓渦輪機的數量從十五座降到九座。
Pierce's compromise reduces the number of turbines from fifteen down to nine.
這樣的電力供應量至少還可供近一萬一千戶人家。
This is still the equivalent electrical power to fair eleven thousand homes.
還是有很多的電力的。
So there's still alot power.
最需要的發生的事總是沒發生，倒是最不需要的事總是在發生。
Exactly the opposite is happening, to the very thing that needs to happen.
這些事應該要加緊腳步去做的，但事實上，它們卻越來越慢。
These things need to be speeded up, and actually, they're getting slowed down.
很多政客都在談論這些事，但真正要面對它們時，
Plenty of politicians are talking about it, but when it comes down to it,
它們就是不會成真。告訴你們，它們就是不會成真。
It's just not happening. It's Just not happening, folks.
人民需求越強烈，政府才會著手進行，
Governments will only go as far as the population demands.
這代表我們需要史無前例的大規模抗議。
And that means mass protest on unprecedented scale.
如果你想要讓你的議題快速升溫
Direct action like this is essential,
像這樣直接的行動就很重要。
if you were going to turn an issue around in a short period of time.
我們發現從女權運動開始，歷史上有很多這樣的案例。
We've found that many many times in the past, from the suffragettes onwards.
在我們這個年代，有很多很多的革命、危機發生，
The very fact that the crisis is taking place in our generations is happening right now,
證明我們是一群極具能力的人。
means we are tremendously powerful people.
所以絕望、"我沒辦法做甚麼"的想法，是沒有道理的。
So this position of despair, and I can't do anything, there's no point.
這是完全不符合邏輯，完全相反的。
It's completely illogically, it's exactly the opposite
他們在計畫著
要將隧道加倍。
夏慕尼區的人終於覺醒了。
我們組成了抗議團體，
對卡車說"不"。
這樣才能減少那些無意義的運輸。
整個團隊都在很拼命，
但我們的人數還是不夠。
我們也不知道我們有沒有這樣的能力
可以去影響
鼓吹興建道路的人。
政府、歐洲，全部都一樣。
他們都一樣是有智慧的人。
但他們需要
真的去完成一些事情。
而不是每次都只想到要凍蒜。
人類完成了許多偉大的事，我們可以做出很多不可思議的事情。
There's no shortage of great matter in the species, we can do some amazing things.
但我不覺得我們有聰明的去思考過，我們該如何運用我們的資源。
But I don't think we been very smart about how we use our resources.
我們將美麗的資源消耗殆盡
How we quite literally burn up something as beautiful and useful as all.
我們這樣將他消耗殆盡，就這樣，沒了，用完了。
We literally burn it up. That's it, it's gone, it's done.
我相信有很多人現在開始不再抱持幻想了，
I think most people were becoming disenchanted by this point.
我們開始不在幻想這是人類文明的黃金年代，
We'd stop believing that this was the golden era of human civilization,
而開始質疑我們全體的價值觀。
and started questioning our collective values.
我只希望，一個慘絕人寰的災難像Katrina颶風
All I can hope is, an incredible disasters like Katrina,
和一些可怕的戰爭，還有許多正在發生在世界各地的事
and the horrible wars comes out and what not, that are going on around the world
能夠點醒我們。
will snap us out of it.
讓看清楚我們現在是不是在朝對全體人類有益的方向前進。
Let's see if it's headed in the right direction for the good of mankind.
因為這次天災，我獲得了很多，我之前是個典型的消費者，
For this disaster, I had a lot of stuff, I was a classic consumer,
但經過這兩年，我學習到很多跟快樂還有有關追求快樂的想法。
Two years later, I've learned lot about happiness and the pursuit thereof.
快樂並不是在最先進的科技玩意兒，像最新的電動牙刷或之類的。
The happiness is not in the latest gadgets, the latest electric tooth brush, or something like that.
這些東西，都不是生活的重點。至少對我而言不是。
All of that stuff. It's just not the stuff of life. Not for me anyway.
送交聯合國有關於解決氣候變遷的提案
歐盟、英國、中國、非洲、世界銀行均同意
氣候科學家可以測量我們還可以安全地燃燒多少剩餘的石化燃料。
Climate scientist can estimate how much of the remaining fossil fuels we can safely burn.
這個數字叫做"全球限額"
This amount is called the "global cap."
在這個提案底下，全世界的政府都必須聯合簽屬國際協議書，
Under this proposal, the world governments will make a binding into international agreement
詳細規畫該怎麼分配這個限額。
detailing how to distribute the global cap.
這計畫越早實行的話，
The earlier the start takes,
就有越多的機會我們可以避免引起難以控制的氣候變遷。
of greater the chance of not triggering runaway climate change.
第一年全球總排放量，假設2012年好了，會以那年當排放作基準。
The total global emissions for the first year, say 2012, will be set for that current level.
每年排放都會縮減，一直到2065年，就會接近零。
Every year following they'll shrink until by about 2065, they're almost zero.
一開始，依照每個國家的消耗量來分配排放的配額。
Initially, each country would be allocated an emissions quota,
一開始，依照每個國家的消耗量來分配排放的配額
according to how much they currently consume.
但是這世界會隨時間改變，
But this would change over time
美國會將排放量降低至相較於現在的90%，
America would slash its emissions 90% from its current over consuming position.
歐洲也會大量減少，中國也是。
Europe too would decrease massively, as would China.
但印度跟非洲會一直增加到2025年，
But India and Africa would increase until by about 2025.
地球上每個人都會有一樣的權利來分享地球的資源。
Each human being on the planet would have equal rights to the earth's resources.
平均分配是唯一符合道德的選擇，
Equity is the only option morally,
而且實際上開發中國家絕不肯簽對他們不益的條約。
and also practically as the developing countries won't sign up for anything less.
但總排放量還是會逐年減少。
But total emissions would then keep decreasing every year.
到2065年時我們就不再使用石化燃料
Until by 2065 we'll have waned ourselves off of fossil fuels
並阻止氣候變遷最嚴重的影響
and prevented the worst impacts of climate change.
至於每個國家該如何分攤，檯面上有很多種選擇。
As to how each country divvies up its share to the system, there were various options on the table.
最被看好的是個人二氧化碳碳配給。
The most promising of which individual carbon rationing.
Morrison先生現在來解釋。
Mr. W.S Morrison is here to explain.
當在戰爭情況下，我們在一段時間內缺乏一些特定的食物。
If in the culture of war, we are short for a time of this or that article of food.
配給能給我們每個人，不管是窮人或有錢人。
Rationing, will give every one, rich and poor alike,
每個人都能享有一樣的物資。
an equal share of all its goods.
在這樣的計畫下。英國每個人都會有一個每年碳排放許可量。
Down to the scheme. Everyone in UK would be allocated to annual carbon allowance.
使用電力就像使用超市的顧客忠誠卡一樣
So the electronic loyalty as the supermarket loyalty card,
每次我們消費非再生資源時，點數就會被扣除。
points will be deducted every time we buy or use non-renewable energy.
舉例來說，就像在家使用家電，
For example, using electricity to power appliances in the home,
或搭飛機去某地方旅行，或甚至是買汽油車或...
or traveling somewhere by plane, or even buying petro-fuel for the car…
最好的方式就是靠自己節制，
The best way you can help is by rationing yourselves,
我確定如此你們就能為自己買到最公平的一份。
I'm sure that all of you will buy your fair share and no more.
機場數量在世界各地擴張，
Airports were expanding all over the world,
如此才能應付因民眾需求而爆增的廉價航空班機。
to cope with the exploding number of cheap flights we were all demanding.
而Jeh則無所不用其極的去參與這場盛會。
And Jeh was doing everything he could to join the party.
機會最終就是要把握並加以利用。
Ultimately, the odd is to hug and then kick.
她說系統是要付費的，你說那是不要付費的。你是哪根筋不對?
She saying the PS is been payable, you're saying the PS is not been payable. What's wrong with you?
現在
Now!
該還是不該，我有問這個問題了吧?還是我沒問?
Yes or no? That I ask you the question, or did I not ask the question?
你被停職了，你也被停職了。都給我出去。
You're suspended, you're suspended. Both of you go out now.
這會他X的花超過你十分鐘時間去清理嗎?給我仔細刷。
Did it take ****more than 10  minute to clean this? Keep paint with you.
這都是一天的工作內容，哈哈...
It's all in a day's work, haha...
維護好我飛機對我很重要，OK!?
Maintaining my plane means something to me, ok!?
如果我再看到我的梯階像這樣，
If I see my step ladder like this,
如果再讓我找到一片灰塵，你就被革職了。
and if I find one piece of dirt, you'll be fired.
OK?
Ok?
Jeh Wadia先生
我現在想要
給你
你們的航空營運許可
你們可以開始營運了
你擁有一家航空公司了。
2007年六月十一日，在Bedford的一間旅館房間裡，
June 11. 2007, in the hotel room in  Bedford.
Piers正在修改自己的演講，為了今晚與當地發展委員會的最後一戰。
Pierce is polishing his speech for tonight showdown with the local planning committee.
這委員會有權力核准的這份申請。
This committee can approve this application.
如果你們這麼作，你們就展現了勇氣跟領導魄力
If you do, you would show courage and leadership.
他只有六分鐘去說服他們批准它的風力發電廠計畫。
He has just six minutes to convince them to approve his wind farm.
我有絕對的把握，就是如果你們批准這項計畫，
I'm absolutely confident, that if you approve this project,
你們以後一定會回頭看這個決定，然後說"感謝老天我們當初答應了"
you'll look back on the decision and say "Thank goodness we said yes."
但他的申請被委員們否決了，
But the committee rejected pierce's application,
認為他的發電廠在一片Bedfordshire的好風景中會太過顯眼
saying that his wind farm would be conspicuous and out of place in the Bedfordshire landscape,
會減低民眾享受附近步道的樂趣
that it would decrease enjoyment of nearby foot paths
也會為古蹟建築及歷史遺跡帶來負面影響
and negatively impact the listed buildings and the nation's monuments.
也就是說，它們會破換景觀
In other words, it would spoil the view.
喔是的，我很開心提案被駁回了。
Oh we're delighted that it's been refused, yes.
完美的結局。
It's a wonderful result.
這證明了只要你努力點，去檢視所有的證據，
It just shows if you work hard, if you look at all the facts,
秉著公正持恆的態度，你就可以得到好的結果。
if you do with fair and balance, you can get a good outcome.
十人反對對一個人支持，也有可能是十一個人對一個人。
10 against, one in favor, might even be 11 against one in favor.
總之只有一個人，他確實舉了贊成。
But there only one guy who actually, actually votes in favor.
開心點吧
Cheers, man.
嗨媽，我是Piers，我想是十人或十一人對一個人。
Hi, mom. It's Piers. I think it's 10 to one or 11 to one against.
對, 很X，真是浪費時間，每個人都是。
Yeah, it's ****, waste of time, rest of them.
坦白講，這不會有任何差別...
I could have said, be honest. It wouldn't make any difference…
我們當然擔心全球暖化
Of course we're worried about global warming,
我是說，一定有一些事是我們都很關心的。
I mean, it's got to be something we all concerned about.
如果我們盡我們的一份心力去節約，並尋找再生能源。
I mean, we're doing our bit to try conserve, and looking for renewable energy.
當然，一定的。我是說，我們是地球的一份子嘛，哈哈…對啊。
Of course, absolutely, yeah, I mean, we're part of the world…haha...yes.
這都是因為全球暖化。
And it is global warming.
第一次，科學家確定了氣候變遷與我們惡劣的天氣之間的關聯性
For the first time, Scientists confirm the link between climate change and our awful weather.
救護工作艱困的進行，而Bedfordshire…
An emergency services scramble and Bedfordshire…
洪水淹沒所經之處，
And the flood water finally work their way along the great tubes,
Bedfordshire其他地區也無一倖免。
other parts of Bedfordshire didn't escape, either.
我們在這住了四十年，我們從來沒有...
We've lived at here for forty years, and we've never ever…
沒看過這樣的景象。
have anything like this.
...緬甸在這次Nargis風災有八萬民罹難者...
… 80000 fatality in Burma today after cyclone Nargis…
...危機降臨西歐，荷蘭現在嚴格實施飲用水配給，法國...
… emergency across Western Europe with drinking water strictly rationing in Holland, France..
森林大火橫掃拉斯維加斯，不幸地...
Forest fire is still sweep across Vegas. Unfortunately, ...
Lord Clarkson表示，讓駕駛上街的代價預估要三十萬英鎊...
30 million pounds, price worth paying for motorists right to drive, said Lord Clarkson..
這是對英國酒業的好消息...
Good news for the UK wine industries, especially…
…紐澳良不會在這時間重建，路伊斯安納州政府表示…
… New Orleans will not be rebuilt at this time, the Louisiana government…
...印度水壩的潰堤將會結束巴基斯坦飲用水的危機
...Total Destruction of Indian Dams would end Pakistan's drinking water crisis.
隨著美國總圖決定繼續...因為...
As U.S president's choices to continue… out because of….
...舊金山異常的熱浪襲擊整個加州...
…San Francisco extraordinary heat wave continue hit in Los Angeles…
極端的氣候越來越頻繁的出現在地球上各個角落...
…Extreme weather somewhere around the planet increasing in these days…
三千五百萬的中國難民...
35 million Chinese refugees…
在阿爾卑斯山滑雪的時代已經結束了...
Skiing in the Alps is over…
第四頻道紀錄片，質疑地球暖化是真的再發生，還是只是自然...
…Channel Four documentaries ask is global warming really happening, or natural…
地面溫度創攝氏六十一度新高...
…61 degrees centigrade the highest land temperature…
超過一億的民眾今晚無家可歸...
More than a hundred million people are homeless tonight…
西伯利亞的甲烷不斷排出...
Methane emitted… in Siberia…
印尼最近找到樹了，但五起的石油危機...
The last Indonesian tree found, but five fuel crisis…
...今天起歐盟將永久的關閉...
…European Union today permanently closed all of it…
...必須為糧食生產做好未雨綢繆的準備...
...must be reserved for food production…
...昨天晚上底三十英呎的水災席捲而來，使得倫敦再次汪洋一片...
… London Is under water again, as last night 30 foot storm surge overcame…
紐西蘭封鎖其邊界使得讓二千兩百萬民眾困在...
New Zealand has also now closed its borders leaving 22 million stranded…
...中東與歐洲大陸的難民...
...refugees in middle east and continental Europe…
...科學家估計超過一半的物種已經絕種，而生態系統也在瓦解中...
...half of the species are now extinct, scientist estimate, and eco systems are collapsing…
…超過兩度，我們現在已經無法阻止失控的氣候變遷...
…passing 2 degrees, we cannot now stop runaway climate change…
人數就是太多了，所以饑荒仍持續存在著
There are simply too many people to feed and are remained famine…
...自殺率成長了百分之八百...
...suicide rates increasing eight hundred percent…
亞馬遜流域的雨林火災仍然持續著...
The Amazon rain forest is still burning…
無法狠下心來吃掉自己的貓跟狗的人...
And anyone who cannot bear to eat their own cats and dogs…
...我們進入全世界第八次的食物危機...
…we are entering the eighth world food crisis…
全世界目前的溫度上升超過四度...
The world temperature today is passing 4 degrees…
...報復的核彈攻擊...
…retaliation nuclear strike…
我們不會是第一個毀掉自己的物種
We wouldn't be the first life form to wipe itself out.
但特別的是，我們是在知曉的情況下做的。
But what would be unique about us, is that we did it knowingly.
這樣又該怎麼解釋呢?
And what's that say about us?
我一直在問一個問題，
The question I've been asking is,
我們為什麼不在我們還有機會時拯救我們自己?
why didn't we save ourselves when we had the chance?
答案是因為在某種程度上，我們不確定自己是否值得被拯救嗎?
Is the answer because on some level, we weren't sure if we were worth saving?
在爬山的時候，
我們會把繩索繫在一起。
我跟你冒的險是一樣的。
我們知道全球暖化
的腳步會越來越快。
所以事態也會越來越嚴重。
對每個人都一樣。
請往飛機前進，然後負責好自己的東西。
Please proceed near the aircraft, and take care of the responsibility.
你知道，要是我們每個人都能團結，那所能做的足以改變世界。
You know if all of us stood united, in terms, the world would be different in every way,
不幸的，這不是事實。
Unfortunately, that's not the reality.
如果我們連地球上窮困都無法弭平，
If we can not even stand united on eradicating poverty in the world,
怎麼會時間去管地球的健康呢?
what is the health of the planet has any chance?
透過當一個醫生...
我真的很想要出名。
這並不簡單，需要很大的努力。
但那就是我的夢想。(尼日三角洲科學學校)
我要恭喜你。
我看你的各種資料都沒問題，
可以給你入學許可。
依我看來，近百年來人類使用或不當使用資源，
In my opinion, our use or misuse of resources in the last hundreds years or so,
我大概會重新命名這世代，叫類似...恩...
I probably would rename that…, age…, something like the…
無知的年代
The age of ignorance.
愚蠢的年代
The age of stupid.
未來我們一定會回去伊拉克。
我們會邀請每個人參加史上最大的派對。
那裡將會是個最快樂的地方，
世界上最快樂的地方。
每分每秒，他們拿走我們的石油，然後離開。
我覺得未來每個人
都會責怪我們
就為我們從沒有思考過
該如何保護我們的環境。
我們只知如何獲取利益卻不知保護。
我覺得很詫異。
I just find it, surprising.
在經過這麼多的努力後，我們最後竟是以自殺收場。
That after so much effort, the final act of our existence, should be suicide.
所以我為什麼要建立這個檔案館?
So why did I build this archive?
是想要當作警世的故事。
It's a cautionary tale.
不是為我們，我們已經太遲了。
Not for us. Too late for us.
而是...
But for..., well...,
而是為最終找到這個紀錄的任何人或東西。
for whoever, whatever, eventually finds this recording.
(傳送)
去吧。
And away you go.
結束
結束?
為了制止失控的氣候變遷
2009年12月在哥本哈根制訂的國際協議，
必須要和科學要求一樣強而有力。
我們還有時間
我們還有恰好的時間
本部影片拍攝過程排放94.270公斤的二氧化碳
相當於8個英國人一年的排放量，4個美國人一年的排放量
1000個坦桑尼亞人一年的排放量，
91個使用永續發展方式生活的人一年的排放量
相當於Piers的一具風力發電機六天的發電量，
相當於回收910,000個瓶子，......
雖然電影內容批評的對象
感覺好像跟台灣一點關係也沒有
台灣人民似乎只需要同聲譴責美國、英國等大國就好
但給各位一些數字參考一下
2006年各國每人排放二氧化碳噸數
台灣每人每年13.19公噸
Alvin的美國19.78公噸，為台灣的150%
Fernand的法國6.6公噸，為台灣50%
Piers的英國9.66公噸，為台灣73%
Jeh的印度1.16公噸，為台灣的9%
Layefa的奈及利亞0.77公噸，為台灣的6%
由上面的資料可知
台灣人民在抵抗氣候變遷的任務中，責無旁貸
你還是只把這部電影看完憂鬱無力一下就好嗎?
你還是只是看完以後仇恨美國人為何這樣殘骸地球而已嗎?
不要猶豫了!請一起加入環保的行列吧!!
每天多坐大眾交通工具，少開車、少騎機車
購買食物、飲料時盡量選擇台灣出產食品，以減少碳足跡
每周選擇一兩天吃素，平常也盡量少吃肉，肉類是碳排放的一大原因
隨手關閉電源、列印影印使用雙面或用單面廢紙
夏日冷氣調至26~28度即可...等
還有很多很多可以為地球做的事情
氣候變遷是真實存在並且由人類造成的問題
現在再不下定決心解決，電影的預言就會成真
請告訴你的朋友、鄰居、同事、同學
跟他們說明現在地球遭遇的狀況
大多數的人並不是不願意作
只是不知道氣候變遷後果的嚴重性，和它的的急迫程度
每個人的一點點力量，就可以造成很大的改變
阻止全球暖化，就差你一個而已
你的一切行動，都會影響地球的未來!!!
今天就去開始起而行!